<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Python | Personal Programming Notes]]></title>
  <link href="http://tdongsi.github.io/blog/categories/python/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://tdongsi.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-02-14T14:27:27-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://tdongsi.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Cuong Dong-Si]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mocking Current Date and Time in Python]]></title>
    <link href="http://tdongsi.github.io/blog/2016/01/27/python-post-1/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-27T17:36:53-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://tdongsi.github.io/blog/2016/01/27/python-post-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Calendar types</h3>

<p>There are surprisingly many types of calendar. Some of them are:</p>

<ol>
<li><strong>Regular Calendar</strong>: regular solar calendar date range as we know.

<ul>
<li>Example: January 01, 2006 to December 31, 2006.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lunar_calendar"><strong>Lunar Calendar</strong></a>: based on cycles of the lunar phases.

<ul>
<li>Example: January 29, 2006 to February 17, 2007.</li>
<li>A lunar year is defined as 12 lunations, which is about 354 days.</li>
<li>In every two or three years, a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lunisolar_calendar">thirteenth-month</a> (intercalary month or leap month) is added to bring the calendar year into synchronisation with the solar year.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Fiscal Calendar</strong>: a company’s selected calendar date range for required SEC financial statement filing.

<ul>
<li>Example: August 01, 2005 to July 31, 2006 is my company&rsquo;s fiscal year 2006.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Tax Calendar</strong>: A number sequence representing weeks in a Tax year which begins right after the US Tax Day.

<ul>
<li>Example: April 16, 2005 to April 15, 2006.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Retail Calendar</strong>: also known as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/4%E2%80%934%E2%80%935_calendar">4-4-5 Calendar</a> or 544 calendar. 544 describes the number of weeks for a given quarter. Each quarter begins with a 5 week &ldquo;month&rdquo;, followed by 2 four week &ldquo;months&rdquo;.

<ul>
<li>Example: July 31, 2005 to July 29, 2006.</li>
<li>Why? This calendar ensures all 4 quarters in a calendar year are equal. This allows comparing weekly data (e.g., retail sales) to the prior year without correcting for times when regular calendar weeks break across months or quarters.</li>
<li>How? It usually uses the same end month as the fiscal calendar and each retail week consists of Sunday through Saturday.

<ul>
<li>The retail year end is defined as &ldquo;the last Saturday of the month at the fiscal year end&rdquo;.</li>
<li>If August 1st is Sunday, it is retail calendar&rsquo;s starting date. The Saturday July 31st is the last Saturday and end of the last retail year.</li>
<li>If August 1st is Monday, then Saturday July 30th is end of the last retail year, and July 31st is the start of the current retail year.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>ISO calendar</strong>: provided in Python <code>datetime</code> module.

<ul>
<li>Example: January 02, 2006 to December 31, 2006.</li>
<li>The first week of an ISO year is the first (Gregorian/regular) calendar week of a year containing a Thursday.</li>
<li>Each week starts at Monday and ends at Sunday.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>


<p>Out of the above calendar types, retail calendar seems to have more complex rules. However, this calendar type is frequently used in industries like retail and manufacturing for ease of planning around it.</p>

<h3>Mocking current time in Python</h3>

<p>Due to retail calendar&rsquo;s desirable characteristics, we may have code that work with retail calendars in commercial applications eventually.
I ended up working with a utility Python module for retail calendar with functions which return values based on current time/date.
For example, a utility function to check if a given date is in the current 544 year works like this:</p>

<pre><code class="python Original version">def is_current_year_544(given_date):
    my_today = datetime.date.today()
    if year_start_544(my_today) &lt;= given_date &lt;= year_end_544(my_today):
        return "Y"
    else:
        return "N"
</code></pre>

<p>Some utility functions in that module are even more complicated than this example function.
For those, I think calling <code>today</code> or <code>now</code> inside those functions is a bad design.
They are essentially another <em>variable</em> in those functions (i.e., when do you run?), and it is better to expose that variable as an input parameter.
In addition, being able to specify what &ldquo;today&rdquo; or &ldquo;now&rdquo; value is will make automated unit testing easier.
For example, I want to know how my Python programs work if it runs on a particular date, such as end of retail year July 29, 2006.
A probably better, more testable function would be something like this.</p>

<pre><code class="python More desirable">def is_current_year_544(given_date, run_date = datetime.date.today()):
    if year_start_544(run_date) &lt;= given_date &lt;= year_end_544(run_date):
        return "Y"
    else:
        return "N"
</code></pre>

<p>However, in reality, you sometimes have to live with the original utility Python module.
Then, the workaround for unit testing it is to &ldquo;mock&rdquo; current date and time, i.e., overriding those returned by <code>today</code> and <code>now</code> methods with some specific values.
In Python, it can be done by using some mocking framework, such as illustrated <a href="http://www.voidspace.org.uk/python/mock/examples.html#partial-mocking">here</a>.
Fortunately, my life was made even easier with <a href="https://github.com/spulec/freezegun"><code>freezegun</code> library</a>.
To install <code>freezegun</code> on Mac OSX, simply run</p>

<pre><code class="plain   ">pip install freezegun
</code></pre>

<p>Using this <code>freezegun</code> library, I can easily specify my &ldquo;current date&rdquo; as &ldquo;July 29, 2006&rdquo; by adding the following decorator with some string &ldquo;2006-07-29&rdquo; for that date.</p>

<pre><code class="python Unit test with mocking">    @freeze_time("2006-07-29")
    def test_year544_end(self):
        """
        Mock today() at 2006-07-29
        """
        self._verify_544_methods()
</code></pre>

<p>For full usage of <code>freezegun</code>, refer to its <a href="https://github.com/spulec/freezegun">quickstart guide</a>.
It should be noted that <code>freezegun</code> can mock <code>datetime</code> calls from other modules and it works great for testing with <code>datetime</code> calls.
However, you might encounter some occasional failures in your unit tests when working with <code>time</code> module.
From my personal experience, in those cases, note that time zones must be accounted for when mocking with <code>time</code> module by specifying <code>tz_offset</code> in the decorator <code>freeze_time</code>.</p>

<h3>External Links</h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/spulec/freezegun">freeze_gun</a></li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/4%E2%80%934%E2%80%935_calendar">Retail Calendar</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.staff.science.uu.nl/~gent0113/calendar/isocalendar.htm">ISO Calendar</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[AWS: Developing With Amazon S3]]></title>
    <link href="http://tdongsi.github.io/blog/2016/01/18/aws-developing-with-amazon-s3/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-18T17:13:28-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://tdongsi.github.io/blog/2016/01/18/aws-developing-with-amazon-s3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Amazon Simple Storage Service or S3 is a simple, scalable web services to store and retrieve data.
This post talks about basic concepts of buckets and objects in S3, basic and advanced operations on objects in S3, and standard development considerations when working with S3 using SDK.</p>

<h3>S3 Buckets and Objects</h3>

<p>Files of any kind such as text, video, photo are stored as objects in S3 <em>buckets</em>.
The bucket name must be globally unique across Amazon S3. It is your responsibility to ensure uniqueness of the bucket name.
A bucket can be <em>versioning-enabled</em>, it will store every version of every object in the bucket.</p>

<p>Each <em>object</em> in S3 is identified by a unique key. The object key is used for upload and retrieval. Alphanumeric characters and <code>!-_.*'/</code> are allowed in a key name.</p>

<p>Bucket naming tips:</p>

<ul>
<li>To ensure uniqueness, you might prefix the bucket name with the name of your organization.</li>
<li>Avoid using a period in the bucket name. Buckets that have a period in the bucket name can cause certificate exception when accessing with HTTPS-based URLs.</li>
</ul>


<p>Object key naming tips:</p>

<ul>
<li>Use prefixes and <code>/</code> (or other delimiters) to logically group your objects. For example, <code>prog/java/arrays.html</code>. There is no hierarchy of objects (e.g., folder) or nested buckets in S3.

<ul>
<li>However, the Amazon S3 console supports the <a href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonS3/latest/UG/FolderOperations.html">folder concept</a> for convenience and usability. Amazon S3 does this by using key name prefixes for objects.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>For performance and scalability, consider using hash as the outermost prefix, in addition to other logical grouping prefixes. See &ldquo;Programming Considerations&rdquo; section below.</li>
</ul>


<h3>Operations on Objects</h3>

<p>Basic operations on S3 objects and buckets are:</p>

<ul>
<li>Put: upload or copy object, up to 5 GB. You can use multi-part upload API for larger objects up to 5 TB.</li>
<li>Get: Retrieve a whole object or part of an object.</li>
<li><a href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonS3/latest/dev/ListingKeysHierarchy.html">List Keys</a>: List object keys by prefix and delimiter.</li>
<li>Delete: Delete one or more objects.

<ul>
<li>If versioning is not enabled, an object is permanently deleted by specifying its key.</li>
<li>If versioning is enabled, you delete an object by specifying a key and version ID. You must delete all versions of an object to remove it.</li>
<li>If versioning is enabled and version is not specified, S3 adds a delete marker to current version of the object. Trying to retrieve an object with a delete marker will returns a &ldquo;404 Not Found&rdquo; error by S3.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Restore: Restore an object archived on Amazon Glacier.</li>
</ul>


<h4>Other operations in S3</h4>

<p>Advanced operations that you should know when situations arise.</p>

<p><strong>Scenario 1</strong>: You want to let users upload files to your buckets for some time duration.
<strong>Solution 1</strong>: You should never share your AWS credentials to let users upload files to your buckets.
Instead, generate a <strong>pre-signed URL</strong> with your security credentials, bucket name, object key, HTTP method (PUT or GET), and expiration date and time.
You share this pre-signed URL to users who will use this to access your S3 buckets.</p>

<p><strong>Scenario 2</strong>: Encryption and strict data security is required.
<strong>Solution 2</strong>: You can enable:</p>

<ul>
<li>Securing data in transit.

<ul>
<li>SSL-encrypted data transfer by using HTTPS</li>
<li><a href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonS3/latest/dev/UsingClientSideEncryption.html">Client-side encryption</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Securing data at rest on AWS server.

<ul>
<li><a href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonS3/latest/dev/serv-side-encryption.html">Server-side encryption</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p><strong>Scenario 3</strong>: You want your web applications that are loaded in one domain to interact with S3 resources in a different domain.
<strong>Solution 3</strong>: Check out <a href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonS3/latest/dev/cors.html">CORS</a>.</p>

<h3>Programming considerations</h3>

<ul>
<li>According to <a href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonS3/latest/dev/request-rate-perf-considerations.html">this guideline</a>, <strong>avoid</strong> using some sequential prefix (e.g., timestamp or alphabetical sequence) for your objects' key names. Instead, prefix the key name with its hash and, optionally, store the original key name in the object&rsquo;s metadata. See examples in the link for more information.</li>
<li>If your application uses fixed buckets, avoid unnecessary requests by checking the existence of buckets. Instead, handle <a href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonS3/latest/API/ErrorResponses.html">NoSuchBucket errors</a> when buckets do not exist.</li>
<li>Set the object metadata before uploading an object. Otherwise, you will have extra requests to do copy operation to update metadata.</li>
<li>Cache bucket and key names if possible.</li>
<li>Set bucket region closest to latency-sensitive users.</li>
<li>Compress objects to reduce the size of data transferred and storage used.</li>
<li>Use an exponential back-off algorithm to retry after failed connection attempts. See <a href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/general/latest/gr/api-retries.html">here</a>.</li>
<li>Enable application logging. For example, <a href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AWSSdkDocsJava/latest/DeveloperGuide/java-dg-logging.html">in Java</a>.</li>
<li>Enable <a href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonS3/latest/dev/ServerLogs.html">server access logging</a>.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[AWS: Getting Started on Mac OSX]]></title>
    <link href="http://tdongsi.github.io/blog/2016/01/17/aws-set-up-aws-credentials-on-mac-osx/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-17T20:57:35-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://tdongsi.github.io/blog/2016/01/17/aws-set-up-aws-credentials-on-mac-osx</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>First, you need to set up your AWS credentials on your Mac by creating the following files at the following specific locations:</p>

<pre><code class="plain">MTVL1288aeea2-82:~ cdongsi$ mkdir ~/.aws
MTVL1288aeea2-82:~ cdongsi$ touch ~/.aws/credentials
MTVL1288aeea2-82:~ cdongsi$ touch ~/.aws/config
</code></pre>

<p>In Windows, the locations of those files will be <code>C:\Users\USERNAME\.aws\credentials</code> and <code>C:\Users\USERNAME\.aws\config</code>, respectively.
You <em>must</em> fill in your AWS access credentials (Access Key ID and Secret Access Key) into the file <code>credentials</code>. Optionally, you can set the default region in the <code>config</code> file.
The content of the files will look like the following:</p>

<pre><code class="plain">MTVL1288aeea2-82:~ cdongsi$ cat ~/.aws/credentials
[default]
aws_access_key_id = your_access_key_id
aws_secret_access_key = your_secret_access_key

MTVL1288aeea2-82:~ cdongsi$ cat ~/.aws/config
[default]
region=us-west-2
</code></pre>

<h3>HelloAws using Java</h3>

<p>Now, you can install AWS Toolkit for Eclipse from <a href="http://aws.amazon.com/eclipse/">this link</a>. Follow the instruction in that page to install AWS Toolkit.</p>

<p>After AWS Toolkit is installed, you are ready to run the first <code>HelloAws</code> Java application. In Eclipse, create a AWS Console application.</p>

<ol>
<li>Click the new orange button on Eclipse taskbar named &ldquo;AWS Toolkit for Eclipse&rdquo;.</li>
<li>Click the link named &ldquo;Create a New AWS Java Project&rdquo;.</li>
<li>Fill in &ldquo;Project name&rdquo; as &ldquo;HelloAws&rdquo;. Check &ldquo;AWS Console Application&rdquo; from &ldquo;AWS SDK for Java Samples&rdquo; panel.</li>
</ol>


<p>Note that the sample generated has the following instruction in its main class. If you haven&rsquo;t do it, follow the steps above to set up your AWS access credentials.</p>

<pre><code class="java">public class AwsConsoleApp {

    /*
     * Before running the code:
     *      Fill in your AWS access credentials in the provided credentials
     *      file template, and be sure to move the file to the default location
     *      (/Users/cdongsi/.aws/credentials) where the sample code will load the
     *      credentials from.
     *      https://console.aws.amazon.com/iam/home?#security_credential
     *
     * WARNING:
     *      To avoid accidental leakage of your credentials, DO NOT keep
     *      the credentials file in your source directory.
     */

    static AmazonEC2      ec2;
    static AmazonS3       s3;
    static AmazonSimpleDB sdb;
</code></pre>

<p>If your AWS credentials are ready, simply run the sample AWS console code as &ldquo;Java Application&rdquo;. The output will look something like this:</p>

<pre><code class="plain">===========================================
Welcome to the AWS Java SDK!
===========================================
You have access to 4 Availability Zones.
You have 0 Amazon EC2 instance(s) running.
You have 0 Amazon SimpleDB domain(s)containing a total of 0 items.
You have 0 Amazon S3 bucket(s), containing 0 objects with a total size of 0 bytes.
</code></pre>

<h3>HelloAws using Python</h3>

<p>To install <a href="http://aws.amazon.com/sdk-for-python/">AWS SDK for Python</a>, run the following the command as instructed in that page:</p>

<pre><code>pip install boto3
</code></pre>

<p>In my case, I used a slightly different command to avoid permission errors on Mac OSX:</p>

<pre><code>pip install boto3 --user
</code></pre>

<p>I use PyCharm/IntelliJ as IDE for Python and, apparently, there is no Python sample for it. In PyCharm, you can use the following Python script as your <code>HelloAws</code> program:</p>

<pre><code class="python">import boto3
from botocore.exceptions import ClientError,NoCredentialsError
import sys

def getS3BucketNumber():

    try:
        s3 = boto3.resource('s3')
        buckets = []
    except NoCredentialsError:
        print "No AWS Credentials"
        sys.exit()

    try:
        bucket_num = len(list(s3.buckets.all()))
        print "Number of buckets: " + str(bucket_num)
        return bucket_num
    except ClientError as ex:
        print(ex)
        return 0

if __name__ == '__main__':
    getS3BucketNumber()
</code></pre>

<p>Note that it is based on the <a href="https://github.com/boto/boto3#quick-start">Quick start on Github</a>. In PyCharm, running the above Python should print the following output:</p>

<pre><code class="plain">Number of buckets: 0
</code></pre>

<h3>Quick note on Python API vs. Java API</h3>

<p>Note that Boto3 SDK for Python support <a href="http://boto3.readthedocs.org/en/latest/guide/resources.html">&ldquo;Resource API&rdquo;</a>.
As opposed to &ldquo;Service Client API&rdquo; like AWS SDK for Java, Resource API provides a higher level interface to the service and it is easier to understand and simpler to use.</p>

<p>For example, the generated example for AWS&rsquo;s Java SDK uses a Service Client API. It uses a class AmazonS3Client that controls the requests you make to the S3 service.
Meanwhile, the Boto3 SDK for Python has classes representing the conceptual resources (e.g., s3.Bucket) that you interact with when using the S3 service.
This is a higher level abstraction compared to a client class like AmazonS3Client making low-level calls to the service API.</p>

<h3>External Links</h3>

<ul>
<li>Python

<ul>
<li><a href="https://boto3.readthedocs.org/en/latest/guide/index.html">Developer Guide</a></li>
<li><a href="https://boto3.readthedocs.org/en/latest/reference/core/index.html">API Documentation</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Java

<ul>
<li><a href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AWSSdkDocsJava/latest/DeveloperGuide/welcome.html">Developer Guide</a></li>
<li><a href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AWSJavaSDK/latest/javadoc/index.html">API Documentation</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Automated Performance Logging and Plotting for Cassandra]]></title>
    <link href="http://tdongsi.github.io/blog/2015/11/14/automated-performance-logging-and-plotting-for-cassandra/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-14T19:57:43-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://tdongsi.github.io/blog/2015/11/14/automated-performance-logging-and-plotting-for-cassandra</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this <a href="https://github.com/tdongsi/python/tree/master/PerformanceLog">mini-project</a>, I created a Python script (PerformanceLog.py) to record JMX values from a running Cassandra instance, using JMXTerm (<a href="http://wiki.cyclopsgroup.org/jmxterm/">http://wiki.cyclopsgroup.org/jmxterm/</a>), and do the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>Put the records into a Cassandra table.</li>
<li>Plot the results.</li>
</ul>


<p>The project is based on a Cassandra interview question found on Glassdoor.</p>

<p>Currently, the first version only works with Windows version of Cassandra (using DataStax Community installer). Developed and tested in Python 2.7.</p>

<h2>Input/Output</h2>

<p><strong>Input</strong></p>

<p>When running the script from command line, the following arguments must be provided:</p>

<ul>
<li>installDir INSTALLDIR:  Path to installation directory.</li>
<li>host HOST: URL string for Cassandra instance. Only localhost tested.</li>
<li>jmxTerm JMXTERM: Path to jmxterm jar file.</li>
<li>osString OSSTRING: String that represents the current OS. Windows: win. Mac: mac. Unix/Linux: linux.</li>
</ul>


<p>Example:</p>

<blockquote><p>python PerformanceLog.py -installDir C:\datastax -host localhost -jmxTerm lib\jmxterm.jar -osString win</p></blockquote>

<p><strong>Output</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>CSV file with each field for each JMX metric.</li>
</ul>


<p>Example:</p>

<blockquote><p>  SSTableCount,DataSize,c95thPercentile</p>

<p>  0,0,0.0</p>

<p>  7,31306299,9337.784849999995</p>

<p>  7,31306299,9262.307649999999</p>

<p>  &hellip;</p></blockquote>

<ul>
<li><p>Records in a Cassandra table</p></li>
<li><p>Performance plot as PNG file (automatically generated from CSV output file)</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Example:</p>

<p><img src="https://dl.dropbox.com/s/0vy2u8b7hb7djjv/jmxMetrics.png" title="Performance Plot" alt="alt text" /></p>

<h2>Python modules</h2>

<ol>
<li>PerformanceLog.py: Main module to run the automated tasks. Please use &ldquo;python PerformanceLog -h&rdquo; for the required arguments. Example call for Windows is in the doc string.</li>
<li>MyLogger.py: Logging support module</li>
<li>CassandraRecord.py: Support module to record metrics into a Cassandra table.</li>
<li>Plotter.py: Support module to plot metrics into plots and save into PNG file.</li>
</ol>


<h3>Automated tasks by the modules</h3>

<ol>
<li>Check if Cassandra is Running</li>
<li>Record certain JMX Metrics</li>
<li>Runs the external tool Cassandra Stress</li>
<li>Once the stress session has completed, stop recording JMX Metrics</li>
<li>Record the metrics back into a Cassandra Table</li>
<li>Graph the results (create these graphs at the end of the run).</li>
</ol>


<h2>External Python libraries required</h2>

<h4>For CassandraRecord.py</h4>

<p>This module requires Datastax&rsquo;s Python driver: <a href="http://datastax.github.io/python-driver/installation.html">http://datastax.github.io/python-driver/installation.html</a></p>

<h4>For Plotter.py</h4>

<p>This Python module used Matplotlib library. Please install the following Python libraries: matplotlib, numpy, dateutil, pytz, pyparsing, six (optionally: pillow, pycairo, tornado, wxpython, pyside, pyqt, ghostscript, miktex, ffmpeg, mencoder, avconv, or imagemagick).</p>

<p>Installation of these Python libraries are straight-forward on Linux and Win32. On Win64, please find their installers here: <a href="http://www.lfd.uci.edu/~gohlke/pythonlibs/">http://www.lfd.uci.edu/~gohlke/pythonlibs/</a></p>

<h2>Other files</h2>

<p>The following output files are produced. For consistency check, they are left behind.
In the final version of the script, they may be cleaned up accordingly.</p>

<ul>
<li>tempout: Output from JmxTerm session</li>
<li>jmxMetrics.csv: The cvs file that records the interested JMX metrics.</li>
<li>CassandraTest.log: The log file for the script.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
