<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Perl | Personal Programming Notes]]></title>
  <link href="http://tdongsi.github.io/blog/categories/perl/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://tdongsi.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-01-21T23:50:13-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://tdongsi.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Cuong Dong-Si]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Unicode in Perl]]></title>
    <link href="http://tdongsi.github.io/blog/2015/11/18/unicode-in-perl/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-18T15:40:20-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://tdongsi.github.io/blog/2015/11/18/unicode-in-perl</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For automation in Perl, Unicode can be tricky, especially when you want your automated jobs/tests to work across platforms (Windows and *nix). If you have a choice, another scripting language like Python may be better off in dealing with Unicode texts. If you don&rsquo;t have a choice and must use Perl (specifically Perl 5) like I used to, some of these tips may help get you started.</p>

<p>The most common code snippet that I used in my Perl codes when dealing with Unicode texts is this Unicode preamble:</p>

<pre><code class="perl Unicode preamble">#!/usr/bin/env perl
use strict;

##############################################################
#### Unicode preamble
use utf8;      # so literals and identifiers in Perl scripts can be in UTF-8
use warnings;  # on by default
use warnings  qw(FATAL utf8);    # fatalize encoding glitches
use open      qw(:std :utf8);    # undeclared streams in UTF-8
use charnames qw(:full :short);  # unneeded in v5.16

##############################################################

my $name = '你好世界';
my $checkPrint = "Print Unicode variable: $name \n";
print $checkPrint;
</code></pre>

<p>The first two lines are standard and should be included in any Perl script. The rest are specifically for dealing with UTF-8 (the most commonly used encoding of Unicode). Another useful code snippet is for printing Unicode codepoints (Quiz: what is the difference between a codepoint and its encoding?):</p>

<pre><code class="perl Print Unicode codepoints">my $unicode_helloworld = "\x{4F60}\x{597D}\x{4E16}\x{754C}";
print "Unicode codepoints: $unicode_helloworld\n";
</code></pre>

<p>More recipes for working with Unicode in Perl 5 can be found in References below.</p>

<p>One dilemma you might be facing when your Perl codes run in Windows is to choose which encoding for your script files: ANSI or UTF-8. In my own experience:</p>

<ul>
<li>If the script file encoding is ANSI, I usually have better luck in &ldquo;What you see is what you get&rdquo; department: for example, files created in filesystem have the filenames with same Unicode characters, such as Japanese/Chinese characters, in Perl scripts. The downside of ANSI encoding is when I try to do regex matching of those Japanese/Chinese characters, I get &ldquo;malformed regex&rdquo; error.</li>
<li>If the script file encoding is UTF-8, the files created in filesystem usually have different Japanese/Chinese characters from those in Perl scripts. However, Japanese/Chinese characters in other places such as log files are matching with ones in Perl scripts. There is no &ldquo;malformed regex&rdquo; error when doing regex matching. However, that correctly formed regex matching may be useless if you need to do matching for output from filesystem such as &ldquo;ls&rdquo; command&rsquo;s output.</li>
</ul>


<!---
Overall, I used ANSI encoding for my Perl scripts as my automation project at that time has to run on Windows/Linux/Mac and interacts regularly with filesystem.
-->


<p>References:</p>

<ol>
<li><a href="http://perldoc.perl.org/perluniintro.html">http://perldoc.perl.org/perluniintro.html</a></li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Perl_Programming/Unicode_UTF-8">https://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Perl_Programming/Unicode_UTF-8</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.perl.com/pub/2012/04/perlunicook-standard-preamble.html">http://www.perl.com/pub/2012/04/perlunicook-standard-preamble.html</a></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
