<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Sql | Personal Programming Notes]]></title>
  <link href="http://tdongsi.github.io/blog/categories/sql/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://tdongsi.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2021-08-27T20:57:21-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://tdongsi.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Cuong Dong-Si]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Analytic Functions in MySQL]]></title>
    <link href="http://tdongsi.github.io/blog/2016/08/17/analytic-functions-in-mysql/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-17T23:12:54-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://tdongsi.github.io/blog/2016/08/17/analytic-functions-in-mysql</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>MySQL has traditionally lagged behind in support for the SQL standard.
Unfortunately, from my experience, MySQL is often used as the sandbox for SQL code challenges and interviews.
If you are used to work with <a href="https://my.vertica.com/docs/7.1.x/HTML/index.htm#Authoring/SQLReferenceManual/SQLReferenceManual.htm">Vertica SQL</a>, writing SQL statements in MySQL can be challenging exercises, NOT necessarily in a good way, because many useful features are not supported.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>WITH clause</h3>

<p>As discussed in this <a href="/blog/2016/02/03/vertica-6-with-clause/">blog post</a>, <code>WITH</code> clause syntax, also known as <em>Common Table Expressions</em> (CTE), is thankfully supported in Vertica.
In summary, <code>WITH</code> clause allows us to arrange sub-queries, usually intermediate steps, in a complex SQL query in sequential, logical order.
This will make the complex queries easier to compose and read: we can write steps by steps of the query from top to bottom like a story (i.e., <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Literate_programming">literate programming</a>).
Unfortunately, <code>WITH</code> clause is not supported by MySQL although this feature has been requested since <a href="https://bugs.mysql.com/bug.php?id=16244">2006</a>.
There are <a href="http://guilhembichot.blogspot.fr/2013/11/with-recursive-and-mysql.html">work-arounds</a> for MySQL&rsquo;s lack of CTE, but the easiest way is probably to revert back to using nested subqueries.</p>

<p>Personally, lack of <code>WITH</code> clause support in MySQL is my greatest hindrance as I often ended up writing queries using <code>WITH</code> clauses as first draft before rewriting those queries using nested subqueries.
This might appear clumsy in SQL interviews even though writing SQL codes with CTE instead of subqueries is the recommended practice for maintainable code.</p>

<h3>Analytic functions</h3>

<p>Another regrettable hindrance when working in MySQL is its lack of analytic functions such as <code>ROW_NUMBER</code>, <code>RANK</code> and <code>DENSE_RANK</code>.
Those <a href="https://my.vertica.com/docs/7.1.x/HTML/index.htm#Authoring/SQLReferenceManual/Functions/Analytic/AnalyticFunctions.htm">analytic functions</a> are supported in Vertica.
The difference between these three functions can be a bit subtle, and would be best described in the following example:</p>

<pre><code class="sql Example of ROW_NUMBER, RANK, and DENSE_RANK functions">SELECT customer_name, SUM(annual_income),
ROW_NUMBER () OVER (ORDER BY TO_CHAR(SUM(annual_income),'100000') DESC) row_number, 
RANK () OVER (ORDER BY TO_CHAR(SUM(annual_income),'100000') DESC) rank, 
DENSE_RANK () OVER (ORDER BY TO_CHAR(SUM(annual_income),'100000') DESC) dense_rank 
FROM customer_dimension
GROUP BY customer_name
LIMIT 15;
</code></pre>

<p>The outputs of these functions are only different if there are duplicates in <code>SUM(annual_income)</code> value, as seen in rows 75-81 in the example output below:</p>

<table border="1"><tr BGCOLOR="#CCCCFF"><th>customer_name</th><th>SUM</th><th>row_number</th><th>rank</th><th>dense_rank</th></tr>
<tr><td>Theodore R. King</td><td>97444</td><td>71</td><td>71</td><td>71</td></tr>
<tr><td>Laura Y. Pavlov</td><td>97417</td><td>72</td><td>72</td><td>72</td></tr>
<tr><td>Carla . Garcia</td><td>97371</td><td>73</td><td>73</td><td>73</td></tr>
<tr><td>Jack Z. Miller</td><td>97356</td><td>74</td><td>74</td><td>74</td></tr>
<tr><td>Steve W. Williams</td><td>97343</td><td>75</td><td>75</td><td>75</td></tr>
<tr><td>Lauren Y. Rodriguez</td><td>97343</td><td>76</td><td>75</td><td>75</td></tr>
<tr><td>Lucas . Webber</td><td>97318</td><td>77</td><td>77</td><td>76</td></tr>
<tr><td>Sarah N. Moore</td><td>97243</td><td>78</td><td>78</td><td>77</td></tr>
<tr><td>Lucas O. Li</td><td>97184</td><td>79</td><td>79</td><td>78</td></tr>
<tr><td>Doug K. Reyes</td><td>97166</td><td>80</td><td>80</td><td>79</td></tr>
<tr><td>Michael . Weaver</td><td>97162</td><td>81</td><td>81</td><td>80</td></tr>
</table>


<p><br/></p>

<p>Sadly, these useful analytic functions are not supported in MySQL.
Fortunately, MySQL supports user variables in SQL queries and we can reproduce those functionalities in MySQL using variables and subqueries as follows:</p>

<pre><code class="sql ROW_NUMBER, RANK, and DENSE_RANK functions in MySQL">-- In Vertica
SELECT 
ROW_NUMBER () OVER (PARTITION BY col_1, col_2 ORDER BY col_3 DESC) AS row_number,
RANK () OVER (PARTITION BY col_1, col_2 ORDER BY col_3 DESC) AS rank,
DENSE_RANK () OVER (PARTITION BY col_1, col_2 ORDER BY col_3 DESC) AS dense_rank,
t.* 
FROM table_1 t

-- In MySQL
SELECT
@row_num:=IF(@prev_col_1=t.col_1 AND @prev_col_2=t.col_2, @row_num+1, 1) AS row_number,
@rank:=IF(@prev_col_1=t.col_1 AND @prev_col_2=t.col_2 AND @prev_col_3=col_3, @rank, @row_num) AS rank,
@dense:=IF(@prev_col_1=t.col_1 AND @prev_col_2=t.col_2, IF(@prev_col_3=col_3, @dense, @dense+1), 1) AS dense_rank,
@prev_col_1 = t.col_1,
@prev_col_2 = t.col_2,
@prev_col_3 = t.col_3,
t.*
FROM (SELECT * FROM table_1 ORDER BY col_1, col_2, col_3 DESC) t,
     (SELECT @row_num:=1, @dense:=1, @rank:=1, @prev_col_1:=NULL, @prev_col_2:=NULL, @prev_col_3:=NULL) var
</code></pre>

<p>The MySQL work-around is intentionally generic so that I can adapt it to any use case.
In addition, it intentionally has a single pass (no <code>SET</code> statements, temporary table) since most SQL code challenges expect a single query.
Finally, note that the above MySQL solution is intentionally incomplete to make it less convoluted.
You need to put that solution in a subquery and <code>SELECT</code> only relevant columns from it.</p>

<p>As an example, the above code template is used to solve <a href="https://leetcode.com/problems/rank-scores/">this Rank Scores problem</a>.
In summary, the question asks for <code>DENSE_RANK</code> functionality to be applied on Score column.</p>

<pre><code class="plain Input table">+----+-------+
| Id | Score |
+----+-------+
| 1  | 3.50  |
| 2  | 3.65  |
| 3  | 4.00  |
| 4  | 3.85  |
| 5  | 4.00  |
| 6  | 3.65  |
+----+-------+
</code></pre>

<pre><code class="plain Expected output">+-------+------+
| Score | Rank |
+-------+------+
| 4.00  | 1    |
| 4.00  | 1    |
| 3.85  | 2    |
| 3.65  | 3    |
| 3.65  | 3    |
| 3.50  | 4    |
+-------+------+
</code></pre>

<p>The solution in Vertica SQL would be straight-forward as follows:</p>

<pre><code class="sql Solution in Vertica SQL">select Score,
DENSE_RANK() OVER (ORDER BY Score DESC) AS Rank
FROM Scores;
</code></pre>

<p>In MySQL, apply the above code template and note that there is no <code>partition clause</code> to arrive at the following solution:</p>

<pre><code class="sql Solution in MySQL">SELECT Score, Rank FROM
( SELECT t.Score,
@dense:=IF(@prev_col2=t.Score, @dense, @dense+1) AS Rank,
@prev_col2:=t.Score
FROM (SELECT Score FROM Scores ORDER BY Score DESC) t, 
(SELECT @dense:=0, @prev_col2:=NULL) var ) x
</code></pre>

<p>Note that the outer <code>SELECT</code> is used to only expose only columns of interest while the main SQL code is enclosed in a subquery.</p>

<h3>Reference</h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.folkstalk.com/2013/03/grouped-row-number-function-mysql.html">ROW_NUMBER in MySQL</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.folkstalk.com/2013/03/grouped-dense-rank-function-mysql-sql-query.html">DENSE_RANK in MySQL</a>: this link actually shows <code>RANK</code> implementation.</li>
<li><a href="https://my.vertica.com/docs/7.1.x/HTML/index.htm#Authoring/SQLReferenceManual/Functions/Analytic/AnalyticFunctions.htm">Vertica Analytic Functions</a></li>
<li><a href="http://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/5.7/en/user-variables.html">MySQL user variables</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[WITH Clause in SQL]]></title>
    <link href="http://tdongsi.github.io/blog/2016/02/03/vertica-6-with-clause/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-03T00:50:48-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://tdongsi.github.io/blog/2016/02/03/vertica-6-with-clause</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am pleasantly surprised that Vertica SQL supports <code>WITH</code> clause, as documented <a href="https://my.vertica.com/docs/7.1.x/HTML/index.htm#Authoring/AnalyzingData/Queries/WITHClausesInSELECT.htm">here</a>.
<code>WITH</code> syntax as a standard is only defined in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SQL:1999">SQL-99</a>, also called <em>Common Table Expressions</em>.
Therefore, I do not usually expect <code>WITH</code> clause since it is a fairly recent feature in most SQL dialects.
For example: <code>WITH</code> clause support is only added into SQLite since Feb 2014.</p>

<p>In summary, the <code>WITH</code> clause allows us to arrange sub-queries in a SQL query in order of human logic.
This will make our query much easier to read: we can read from top to bottom like reading a story (i.e., <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Literate_programming">literate programming</a>).</p>

<!--more-->


<p>For example, we can look into the following <code>SELECT</code> query:</p>

<pre><code class="sql Hard to read">SELECT * FROM (
  SELECT *,
  row_number() OVER (PARTITION BY customer_id ORDER BY last_modify_date DESC) AS rank 
  FROM stg_customer
) sorted_by_modify_date where sorted_by_modify_date.rank =1
</code></pre>

<p>Before <code>WITH</code> clause, SQL scripts are usually hard to read due to nesting of sub-queries.
To understand a SQL statement, we have to find and understand the innermost sub-query first and start working from inside out.
In addition, as shown in the first example, name <code>sorted_by_modify_date</code> following the sub-query makes reading harder, even with meaningful names.
The longer the inner query gets, the more likely the name for that query is pushed out of sight despite the fact that it is important to see an intention revealing name before reading such inner query.</p>

<p>The above example can be made easier to read using <code>WITH</code> clause as follows:</p>

<pre><code class="sql Easy to read">WITH sorted_by_modify_date AS (
    SELECT *, ROW_NUMBER() OVER (PARTITION BY customer_id 
                                  ORDER BY last_modify_date DESC) AS rank 
    FROM stg_customer
)
SELECT * FROM sorted_by_modify_date
WHERE sorted_by_modify_date.rank = 1;  
</code></pre>

<p>As the second example demonstrates, <code>WITH</code> clause solves two problems: 1) names come first, 2) sub-queries are un-nested.
The <code>WITH</code> clause puts the name above the code, like declaring a function with code in the sub-query.
We can pick a meaningful, intention revealing name for it and we can refer to that &ldquo;function&rdquo; in the following sub-queries in the same <code>WITH</code> clause.
Moreover, the most powerful impact of <code>WITH</code> clause is that sub-queries can be un-nested to follow the order and flow of developers' thoughts.
We can define multiple queries for multiple steps, and each of them can refer to the <em>previously</em> defined queries in the same <code>WITH</code> clause.</p>

<p>The following example demonstrates the power of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Literate_programming">literate programming</a> in SQL, enabled by <code>WITH</code> clause:</p>

<pre><code class="sql Traffic classification of a Music website">WITH Total_Traffic AS
(
    SELECT temp.* from temp as clickstream_data
    where .... -- filtering
)
, Rock_Music as
(
    select * from Total_Traffic
    WHERE lower(evar28) LIKE 'rock_mus%'
)
, Instrumental_Music as
(
    select * from Total
    WHERE evar28 LIKE '%[ins_mus]%'
)
, Defined_Traffic as
(
    select * from Rock_Music
    UNION
    select * from Instrumental_Music
)
select traffic_date_key
, count(distinct visitor_id) as unique_visitor
from Defined_Traffic 
group by traffic_date_key
</code></pre>

<p>The purpose of this query is to find the daily number of &ldquo;Defined&rdquo; unique visitors from clickstream data.
Finding daily total unique visitors from Clickstream data is easy and, by subtracting &ldquo;Defined&rdquo; numbers from &ldquo;Total&rdquo; numbers, we can find the &ldquo;Unknown&rdquo; traffic numbers that help determine marketing decisions.
Note that the total &ldquo;defined&rdquo; unique visitor count is NOT equal to sum of all unique visitor counts from each classification (e.g., &ldquo;Rock&rdquo; + &ldquo;Instrumental&rdquo;) since some visitors will listen to both Rock and Instrumental music on the website.</p>

<p>It would be hard, if not impossible, to write such query using only nested sub-queries and achieve the same readability.
The ease of reading is from a combination of top-down code structure and meaningful block names before code blocks, both are properties of <code>WITH</code> clause.</p>

<p>In the past, without <code>WITH</code> clause, we used to create <code>TEMPORARY TABLES</code> in Vertica to save the immediate steps.
Now, we have a native SQL solution in <code>WITH</code> clause and a more powerful technique to create sub-queries.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hive: Introduction]]></title>
    <link href="http://tdongsi.github.io/blog/2015/11/22/programming-hive-chapter-1/"/>
    <updated>2015-11-22T17:22:51-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://tdongsi.github.io/blog/2015/11/22/programming-hive-chapter-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<!---
"Chapter 1: Introduction" of the "Programming Hive" book.
-->


<p>Experimenting Hive with <a href="/blog/2015/11/20/wordcount-sample-in-cloudera-quickstart-vm/">Cloudera Quickstart VM</a>.</p>

<!--more-->


<h3>Introduction</h3>

<p>Hive provides a SQL dialect, called Hive Query Language (HiveQL or HQL) for querying data stored in a Hadoop cluster. SQL knowledge is widespread for a reason; it&rsquo;s an effective, reasonably intuitive model for organizing and using data. Therefore, Hive helps lower the barrier, making transition to Hadoop from traditional relational databases easier for database users such as business analysts.</p>

<p>Note that Hive is more suited for data warehouse applications, where data is relatively static and fast response time is not required. For example, a simple query such as <code>select count(*) from my_table</code> can take several seconds for a very small table (mostly due to startup overhead for MapReduce jobs). Hive is a heavily batch-oriented system: in addition to large startup overheads, it neither provides record-level update, insert, or delete nor transactions. In short, Hive is not a full database (hint: check HBase).</p>

<p>HiveQL does not conform to the ANSI SQL standard (not many do), but it is quite close to MySQL dialect.</p>

<h3>Hive within the Hadoop Ecosystem</h3>

<p>A basic understanding of Hadoop and MapReduce can help you to understand and appreciate how Hive works. Simple examples such as WordCount in my <a href="/blog/2015/11/21/explaining-wordcount-example/">last post</a> can be very involving when using the Hadoop Java API. The API requires Java developers to manage many low-level details, repetitive wiring to/from Mappers and Reducers. The WordCount example&rsquo;s Java implementation can be found <a href="https://wiki.apache.org/hadoop/WordCount">here</a>.</p>

<p>Hive not only eliminates advanced, sometimes repetitive Java coding but also provides a familiar interface to those who know SQL. Hive lets you complete a lot of work with relatively little effort. For example, the same WordCount example in HiveQL can be as simple as:</p>

<pre><code class="sql WordCount example in HiveQL">CREATE TABLE docs (line STRING);

/* Load text files into TABLE docs: each line as a row */
LOAD DATA INPATH 'wordcount.txt' OVERWRITE INTO TABLE docs;

CREATE TABLE word_counts AS
SELECT word, count(1) AS count
FROM
   -- explode will return rows of tokens
  (SELECT explode(split(line, '\s')) AS word
   FROM docs) w
GROUP BY word
ORDER BY word;
</code></pre>

<!--
In the remaining sections of Chapter 1, the authors also discuss various related Hadoop projects such as Pig, Hue, HBase, Spark, Storm, Kafka, etc.
-->

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
